NARRATOR: Previously on Gotham:
You haven't by chance
seen Officer Dougherty?
[GRUNTS]
Supposed to have dinner last
night and he didn't show. No surprise.
- Um, but I haven't seen him today.
- Me neither.
Barbara, we're
doing this for you.
[GASPS THEN SCREAMS]
- He's dead?
- Yeah. He's dead. It's gonna be okay.
Bruce, your father was a true
stoic. He kept his best self hidden.
- Your father was a good man.
- But even good men have secrets.
You have a hard head,
James, just like your father.
Gotham is on a knife edge. But I
won't let it fall apart without a fight.
ESSEN: Just got
wind of three attacks on
Falcone businesses in
different parts of town.
It's Maroni. We're
in a shooting war.
[WOOD CREAKING]
Whoa.
Good morning, child.
We ain't children.
And it ain't morning.
Oh, it will be soon.
A brand-new day.
NEWSMAN [ON TV]: The gang
war rages on here in Gotham.
No one knows what
set this turf war off...
but it is widely believed to be the
result of the longtime power struggle...
between Salvatore Maroni
and Carmine Falcone.
Longtime enemies, these
men have often come to blows...
[NEWSMAN CONTINUES
SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
ALFRED: Still looking
for secrets, are we, sir?
Or just breaking stuff?
Secrets.
ALFRED: Why don't I...?
Whole city's going
doolally around us.
I mean, there's a bloody
war on the streets...
and you're here worrying
about your poor dad.
Yes, I am.
If your father had a secret life,
which I hasten to add he didn't...
I'd know about it, wouldn't I?
A sober, diligent man, he
was. Never out gallivanting.
Home every night like clockwork,
working in this very room.
Yes, I remember.
I wasn't allowed to disturb
him while he was working.
Nobody was.
Classical music, he
would play, for hours.
That's right.
Mom and I would read books or
play board games until he was done.
I remember.
I tried to sneak in to see
him, but the door was locked.
- Was the door always locked, Alfred?
- Yeah, I suppose so, when he was working.
Why, though?
- Why lock the door?
- That's what doors are for, isn't it?
It's in here. It's in this room.
My father's secret.
It's in this room.
I know it. I know it.
Uh... Oh.
[CHICKENS CLUCKING]
[CHATTERING]
Hello, young lady.
I like your style.
COP 1: Put Falcone's guys in
one cell and Maroni's in another.
[INDISTINCT SHOUTING
AND GRUNTING]
COP 2: Shut up.
Get in there.
More where that came from.
Officer Katz, right?
- Yes, sir. Katz, Griffin.
- Word of advice, Katz.
I'm a dead duck around here.
Brass are gonna fire me as
soon as this gang war cools off.
So don't salute me.
Makes you look like a rube.
- Hi. LESLIE: Detective.
- Dr. Thompkins.
- Jim.
Thanks for coming to see me.
It's good to see
you looking so well.
I am well. Much better.
Yes, you are. This is your last
checkup. You are all healed, physically.
But you need to get
some trauma counseling.
Doc, I'm happy. I
am happy to be alive.
Which is why, Jim, I didn't wanna
leave without saying thank you properly.
Thank you for saving my life.
I was glad to do it.
LESLIE: Ms. Kean.
Trauma counseling, like, yesterday. I
have several recommendations for you.
- Really, doc, I'm fine.
- You're not fine.
After what you've been
through, nobody would be fine.
Fine. If you will
be my counselor.
And we do it at my place.
No. I have some trauma training,
but it's not my area of focus.
I like you. Okay? I
can talk to you. Please.
Okay.
- Deal.
- Thank you.
Hmm?
COP: All right, last warning
to all of you: don't be that guy.
Hey, Jim, did you hear the
news? Don Falcone just got hit. Jim.
- What?
- Falcone got hit. Twenty minutes ago.
Maroni's boys blew up his car.
- Wait, he's dead?
- No. He's at the hospital.
But he'll be dead soon enough.
Essen said City Hall and
the bigwigs okayed the hit.
They switched their
support to Maroni.
Maroni? That hothead?
They think he can run this city?
[CELL PHONE RINGING]
Someone had to go. This
war has been bad for business.
Hello?
[GRUNTING]
[SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
[DOOR OPENS THEN CLOSES]
Good morning, good morning.
Oh, Penguin. Thank God. Get me out of
here. Maroni's men will be here any minute.
Yes, I imagine so. Heh.
Mustn't stay long.
I knew I'd regret it if I didn't
say goodbye to you in person.
It was me, old friend.
I did this to you.
I started the war.
From the day I met you,
I was planning your end.
I'm sorry it has
to be in this...
squalid little corner, but...
[SPEAKS IN FRENCH]
Why?
Nothing personal,
I assure you, sir.
You have been a wise
mentor and a good friend.
But business must come first.
I'm gonna take
your place, old man.
I'm gonna be the king of Gotham.
[CHUCKLING]
You?
Never.
You're going to burn in hell.
I do worry about that.
But you first, old friend.
You first.
Nobody move.
[GRUNTS]
- Walk away.
- Shut up.
You're both under arrest
for attempted murder.
Didn't you hear? Falcone is out.
By official decree. Everyone agreed.
I heard.
So release me, Jim.
Get on the winning side.
Winning side, my ass. Maroni's
a fool. He can't replace me.
A thousand rivals will
jump up to challenge him.
There'll be civil war. If I
die now, Gotham falls apart.
I agree. But can you turn things
around? Can you take back control?
Of course.
Two days at my safe house.
I need two days to
make some moves.
Then I'll skin Maroni and
those disloyal scum like rabbits.
OSWALD: Wake up, Napoleon.
Maroni's louts are minutes away from
coming here and cutting your throat.
And the thing is, Jim, they
aren't very fond of me either.
So seriously, you
need to uncuff me. Jim?
- Jim, where the hell did you run off to?
- Harv, I'm in the hospital with Falcone.
- There's nobody here.
- No kidding. What are you doing there?
You gotta get out. They'll be
coming back to finish him off.
Yeah. Any moment now.
- Unless I get him out of here.
- Jim, Jim, Jim.
- I could use some help.
- No way. Are you nuts?
He's a bad man, but he's
the best bad man we got.
If Falcone loses control,
Maroni's too wild to run Gotham.
- There'll be anarchy.
- Yeah, probably.
- But Falcone already lost control.
- And he'll get it back.
Listen, you're all twisted over
what happened to Barbara.
- You're not thinking straight.
- Yeah. Maybe.
But I'm done in this town
anyhow. What do I have to lose?
Your life.
Huh? How about your life?
What the hell are you doing here? I
thought the fix was in with you guys.
[CHUCKLES]
- Can you walk?
- If I have to.
Let's get you out. I'll take
you to your safe house.
My friend, you are
making a terrible mistake.
I'm doing this for the city, not
you. You're the least worst option.
If I didn't think you could take
back control, I'd let you die.
- Just so we're clear.
- We're clear.
You can't leave me here.
Maroni's men will kill me.
- Possible.
- No. No, you arrested us.
We are in your custody.
- That's true.
- You owe me a favor, Jim. You owe me.
- Damn it. LOEB: James Gordon?
Detective Gordon?
Don't kill them.
Morning, fellas. What
can I help you with?
Yes, Gordon. As usual,
wrong place, wrong time.
Go. Now.
Why? So these men
can kill Carmine Falcone?
I have no knowledge of that.
Go. That's an order.
You're a disgrace, Loeb.
I hope to see you behind
bars very soon or dead.
- Whichever.
- Hope?
It's for losers, Jim.
He's all yours.
[GRUNTS]
Jim, Jim, don't shoot. It's me. We gotta
go. There are ambulances in the basement.
Where's your man?
Uh...
About that.
- We gotta take Penguin and Gilzean too.
- Penguin and Gilzean?
I arrested them for attempted
murder. They're in my custody.
Ugh! I don't even wanna argue
with you. Come on, let's go. Go.
Tommy?
[TIRES SCREECHING]
MAN: Boss! Boss, look out!
Get down.
Damn it.
What exactly are we
looking for, Master Bruce?
When I find it, I'll know.
Nobody knows about
this place, right? Nobody?
Nobody. Anybody who did is dead.
We'll be safe here.
Hello.
What's up?
[GARAGE DOOR OPENS]
FISH: I know, I know.
It's astonishing.
Sometimes I astonish myself.
I feel like, uh,
this is all a dream.
I'm gonna wake up soon.
Barbara, you were abducted.
Your parents were
killed in front of you.
Yeah. Yeah, that's real.
I'm talking about
this, now. This...
This is the dream.
I'm gonna wake up,
and he's still alive.
And he's coming for me.
FISH: I thought for sure you
were dead. Let me look at you.
Fish?
Is it real...? Is it really you?
It's me, Butch. I'm home.
My poor baby. What
did they do to you?
Nothing good.
It's him, boss.
Don Maroni.
[CHUCKLES]
Yes, alive and well.
Well, that's a long story.
We need to talk.
I have something you want.
[GRUNTING]
They didn't find my knife.
Ah. So we're saved, then.
It's in my sock.
If you get the chance,
take some of them with us.
I'll try.
- Hey, you.
- Selina, what are you doing here?
- Chilling. How about you?
- Kind of jammed up.
Yeah.
That's too bad.
Oh. That's mime for "Help us out here,"
and totally blow the coolest gig ever.
Just because we kind of sort
of know each other? Right?
[SIGHS]
Hello, fellas. Hmm.
Carmine.
Penguin? Nothing to share?
Well, I have a little something.
I just made a sweet
deal with Maroni.
He just told me I could
have all my territories back...
and all I have
to do in return...
is give him Carmine's head.
Uh, Fish, I need to go lie down.
What did you do to that
poor soul, you sadist?
I assure you...
You will die a slow, painful
death on account of Butch.
You too, Carmine.
You.
We'll keep it simple.
And you?
We're cool. Any questions?
How you gonna kill them?
I love this girl.
[FISH LAUGHS]
BARBARA: Jason
saw right through me.
He knew me instantly.
Like I was naked.
Scary.
But thrilling.
And aren't all the
best guys a little scary?
I was way more scared of Jim
Gordon, first date we went on.
So butch and stern.
That type, they often
have a bad temper.
Hmm. But Jim was a sweetie.
Never laid a finger on me.
It's kind of surprising.
Does he ever hit you?
Me? No. Why? Why would
he hit anyone? Any woman?
You know, out of passion.
I'm sorry. I didn't mean to pry.
Only, I heard you
and Jim were dating.
No.
Uh, yes. We've been on a few dates.
I'm sorry. I didn't think that you knew.
If that makes you
uncomfortable in any way...
No, don't be silly.
I, uh... I'm happy for you.
He's one of the good guys.
Yeah, he is.
Hey, you hungry?
FISH: So there he is.
Fish, you mysterious,
crazy, gorgeous killer, you.
I love you.
[FISH CHUCKLES]
This...
This is delicious. Finally.
- You're hard to kill, old man.
- No. Your people are second-rate.
[SCOFFS]
Ms. Mooney, if I may, a brief
word. I know my life is forfeit.
I speak not for
my sake but yours.
Because after all, I still
love and respect you.
Kill me if you must,
but keep Falcone alive.
As soon as he's dead,
Maroni has no use for you.
You are simply a
threat. He will kill you.
Oh!
You think?
OSWALD: Why would he
need another boss in town?
- Another rival?
- That's where you're wrong, smart guy.
A, she's not a rival,
because she's not a boss.
She's an underboss.
An underboss takes
orders. I don't take orders.
I know that. We're cool. Relax.
- I'm relaxed.
- I don't think you are, babes.
Please don't call me "babes."
You see? Not relaxed.
Babes? Really? It's
a term of endearment.
It means I like you.
Fine, I misspoke.
You're not an underboss and you're
not a babe. You tell me what you are.
What we are, Sal...
are partners.
Whatever you want. Partners.
I'm Partner Number 1, and
you're Partner Number 2.
That's the deal, right? I'm
number one, and you are...?
- Number two. MARONI:
There you go. Simple math.
One, two, babes. Oops.
Sorry. That's the
last time, I swear.
Guys, can you feel
the buzz in the air?
That's victory.
Redemption. Power.
When this old man
dies, a new day begins.
We will rule Gotham.
We're building a dynasty.
We will whip this
town like a rented mule.
Right, babes?
[MEN CHUCKLING]
[CHUCKLES]
All right, relax.
I'm kidding you.
Guys, no, seriously.
Don't call her "babes."
Or "toots" or what have you.
It's a women's-lib thing.
I am relaxed.
[GUNFIRE]
Come on!
[ALL GRUNTING AND SHOUTING]
GORDON: Let's go.
We've been circling
around the subject...
but haven't talked about
what actually happened to you.
What was done to you.
Lee, you're a nice lady.
I could go there, but I'm not
sure you wanna go there with me.
Don't worry about me.
Has Jim told you he loves you?
- Barbara...
- Fair is fair.
And I'm telling you
all my little secrets.
No, he hasn't.
But he will, though, won't he?
You can feel it coming.
Come on, look at you.
You're gorgeous and smart.
Of course he loves you.
Do you love him?
Barbara.
Tell me what happened.
[GUNFIRE AND SHOUTING NEARBY]
If we can get to Seventh without being
spotted by Fish's people, we're home free.
- Then what?
- We find a safe place, regroup.
Maroni's death is a
lucky break for you.
Spoken like a true mafioso.
You're the least worst option. Like you
said, without you, the city falls apart.
Yes, I said that.
And it might be true.
But this has been a long day...
and I've had a long time to
look at this world I've created.
I'm done with this
business. I'm out.
I've got a place down
south I can go to.
- I'm sorry.
- You're sorry?
I know, I'm letting you down.
I'm letting the city down. I know.
[DOOR OPENS NEARBY]
[MEN SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
MAN 1: Think I heard something.
MAN 2: Yeah, flash this way.
Down here, down here.
Okay, plan B.
So you got a place down
south, huh? Nice? On the water?
- Yes.
- Any work for beat-up old cops?
Sure.
How's that sound, Jim?
Beaches, sunshine, fishing...
Yeah. Tempting.
Hello again.
Cat got your tongue?
Yes.
Selina. Boys.
- Bless you.
- Gotta hand it to you, Fish.
You really know
how to stop a show.
I couldn't help myself,
Harvey. The man vexed me.
Crazy move. Possibly a
good move too. We'll see.
The battlefield is in flux.
You could be looking at
the new queen of Gotham.
Congratulations, my dear.
- I'm quitting, Fish. I'm out.
- Does this mean I don't have to kill you?
You're going to retire someplace warm,
lay back, read your little funny papers?
- That was the thought.
- Yeah, nice thought.
[GUNFIRE]
Please, no...
Fish! Where are you?
Go.
Then he left me for a long time.
Alone.
And I slept.
I don't know for how long.
And then he woke me up.
Road trip, he said.
We were halfway
there when I realized...
we were going to
my parents' house.
Go on.
Well, then he tied
them up to a chair.
And, uh, he told
me to talk to them...
about my childhood issues.
So I did.
I just told them whatever
came into my head.
And what came into your head?
You know, just stupid
kid stuff, I guess. Like...
My mom used to call me her
little piggy when I was little.
They threw away my posters.
Never nurtured my self-esteem.
Just slowly, steadily...
grinding away at my soul.
Trying to make me disappear.
That's not kid stuff.
To be fair to them...
they simply never understood me.
They have no clue who I am.
Even when I was killing them,
they just gaped at me like fools.
No understanding.
Barbara, Jason Lennon killed
your parents. You didn't kill them.
Yes, I did.
I stabbed them several times.
And then I slit their throats.
- I'd like to leave now, please.
- You uncomfortable?
How about now?
[DOOR OPENS]
[LOCK CLICKS]
[BARBARA GRUNTING]
[BANGING ON DOOR]
[BUSY SIGNAL ON PHONE]
[ELEVATOR BELL DINGS]
[DOG WHIMPERING]
[GRUNTS]
[YELLS]
[BOTH YELLING AND GRUNTING]
[BARBARA GROWLING WILDLY]
Lee?
She just... She just went crazy.
I told him that
woman was trouble.
[PANTING]
[GRUNTING]
[FISH YELLS]
[BOTH YELL]
Butch. About time.
- Shoot her, Butch.
- Oh, really?
Do as I say, Butch. Shoot her.
What are you doing? Drop him.
My friend, remember
your training.
I order you to shoot her.
Butch, don't listen to him.
He did something to your mind.
I'm your girl.
Remember, I'm your girl.
Kill her now!
[BOTH YELL]
[GROANING]
FISH: Butch.
Oh, my God, what did I do?
I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I would
never hurt you. I love you, Fish.
It's okay. It's not your
fault. I love you too.
He messed with your
mind. It's not your fault.
I'm gonna be fine. You know me.
[OSWALD YELLS THEN BUTCH GRUNTS]
[GROWLS]
Goodbye, Fish.
It's all good.
[BOTH YELL]
No!
[FISH SCREAMS]
[WATER SPLASHES]
I'm the king of Gotham.
[LAUGHING]
I'm the king of Gotham!
Mr. Nygma.
Ms. Kringle.
I just noticed
something really weird.
Oh?
This note Officer
Dougherty left for me...
The first letter of every
line spells out your name.
You see?
N-Y-G-M-A.
Yes.
How... How odd.
What an amazing coincidence.
- Coincidence?
- What else could it be?
- So you know nothing about this?
- I? Me? No. No.
No.
Huh.
[DOOR CLOSES]
[LAUGHING]
DOUGHERTY: You're
the guy that likes riddles.
- Why laugh? It's not funny.
DOUGHERTY: What a creep.
She'll keep digging.
Why did you have
to leave a clue? Why?
Relax.
What can she find? What can she prove?
Nothing. There's no body. Stop worrying.
She looked so sad and angry.
I hate it when she's that way.
KRINGLE: Menacing and weird.
- Please.
Like it matters. Like you
stand a chance with her.
She knows how you feel about
her, and she treats you like dirt.
[SIGHS]
I don't care. I
still love her. Ugh!
Listen to yourself. Be a man!
KRINGLE: You're an
odd man, Mr. Nygma.
You'll do better if she's
a little scared of you.
- Stop talking like that.
DOUGHERTY: No riddles.
KRINGLE: Formal complaints about you.
- Just keeping it real.
What's black and white
and red all over? Stop it!
DOUGHERTY: I wouldn't
quit your day job if I were you.
[LAUGHING]
KRINGLE: He is so weird.
Beautiful, huh? I'm
gonna miss this town.
You won't change your mind?
Town needs you.
No. Gotham needs a lawman
now, not a criminal like me.
A strong lawman.
You looking at me?
Someone needs to grab this
city by the neck and shake it hard.
That's you, Jim. I
know it in my bones.
There's a lot of powerful men
who would disagree with you on that.
FALCONE: Nice knife, huh?
That was your father's. He
gave it to me a long time ago.
A spur-of-the-moment
birthday gift. I said no.
Such a beautiful knife, and I
have men with guns to protect me.
He said, "Take it.
A knife is a good friend
when you have no other."
You were that close?
At one time.
Point of the story, Jim...
your father was the most
honest man I ever met.
But he carried a knife.
ALFRED: Enough searching,
Master B. There's nothing here.
Now, your father was a good
man. A flawed man like anyone else.
- Doesn't mean he had a secret life.
- My intuition is nearly always correct.
Yeah, well...
It's a common delusion, I find.
Arkham's full of men whose
intuitions were always correct.
There are none so blind.
None so blind.
- Marcus Aurelius. Marcus Aurelius.
- What about him?
He was a Roman emperor.
Yes, I'm fully aware
of that, Master Bruce.
And a stoic.
I think I remember he
was a stoic, like my father.
Lucius Fox called
my father a stoic.
Lots of people are called stoic.
It means a hard nut who doesn't
say much. Doesn't mean it's a clue.
It's a philosophy,
Alfred. It's a way of life.
Maybe... Maybe that
as well, I suppose, but...
- Ah!
- Uh-oh.
- What is it, do you think?
- I don't know and I don't care.
- Don't you dare press that button.
- Why not?
It could be a bomb.
Alfred, that seems improbable.
[PROKOFIEV'S "DANCE OF THE
KNIGHTS" PLAYING OVER SPEAKERS]
It's a stereo.
[BRICKS GRINDING]
[English - US -SDH]